Department of Special Collections, Hesburgh Libraries of Notre Dame
American Colonial Currency Collection
- Georgia Currency June 8, 1777GeorgiaJune 8, 1777, GA 06/08/77; ;
  - One-Quarter Dollar65 65, 95; Signers: Edward Langworthy, Nehemiah Wade; Size: 67 x 85mm. (front border design 66 x 83mm; blank back).
    Denominated as one forth of a Continental dollar with a value of 1s3d. The border design is listed by Newman as variety c in that in the right margin the ninth ornament from the bottom has a horizontal line above and below it. Stated as being "for the Support of the Continental Troops, and other Expenses of Government." geometric design in lower right corner stating denomination in dollars and shillings. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 441. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - One-Half Dollar15 15, 96; Signers: Edward Langworthy, Nehemiah Wade; Size: 65 x 82mm. (front border design 65 x 82mm; blank back).
    Denominated as one half of a Continental dollar with a value of 2s6d. The border design is listed by Newman as variety E in that in the bottom margin the thirteenth ornament from the left has a horizontal line to its left and a question mark to its right. Stated as being "for the Support of the Continental Troops, and other Expenses of Government." In the lower right cornet is a geometric design stating denominatin in shillings. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 442. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - Five Dollars83 83, 98; Signers: Joseph Wood, Edward Langworthy, Richard Wylly, William O'Bryen, Nehemiah Wade; Size: 75 x 88mm. (front border design 72 x 83mm; blank back)
    Printed in red and black. This example has the "in" in red. Others have the 'in' in black. On the right is a blue circular seal of a rattlesnake with the legend "Nemo me impune lacesset." (No one will provoke me with impunity). In this example the legend, which is above the snake, is quite rubbed. The bill states the certificate was issued "for the Support of the Continental Troops, and other Expenses of Government." The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 11/16/96 lot 568. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Georgia Currency September 10, 1777GeorgiaSeptember 10, 1777, GA 09/10/77; ;
  An emission of typeset certificates of credit payable in Continental Currency based on the September 10, 1777 resolution to support Continental troops. The issue states "...for the Support of the Continental Troops, and other Expences of Government...". Fractional denominations were printed in black and smaller in size. Dollar denominations were printed in red and black with red circular seals on $1-$4 dollar bills and dark blue circular seals on the higher denominations. Fractional bills had two or three signers while higher denominations had five signers. The denominations printed were: $1/5, $1/2, $4/5, $1, $2, $3, $4, $5, $6, $7 and $8 notes.
  - Seven Dollars3489 3489, 101; Signers: W. Hohendorf, C. F. Chevalier, Richard Wylly, William O'Bryen, Nehemiah Wade.; Size: not available.
    The certificate is printed in red and black ink. In the lower right corner is a blue-black circular seal depicting a liberty cap with a cornucopia and a caduceus; the motto above reads: "Libertas carior auro" (Liberty id dearer than gold). Five signatures in brown ink. The back is blank.
    Courtesy of Early American Numismatic Auctions, Inc. Images used with permission from their on-line auction catalog for the auction of April 21, 1996, lot 445.
  - Four Dollars498 498, 99; Signers: James Habersham, Richard Wylly, William O'Brien, Nehemiah Wade (four signers only).; Size: 77 x 85mm. (front border design 71 x 83mm; blank back).
    Printed in a bright red and black inks with a red circular seal depicting a stag. The left ornamental border has been partly cut off. This denomination usually five signatures (as in the $6 example below) but there are only four signatures on our example, all in brown ink. Note that O'Brien and Wade did not use the empty space but signed sideways (as on the example below). The back is blank.
  - Six Dollars1460 1460, 100; Signers: W. Hohendorf, C. F. Chevalier, Richard Wylly, William O'Bryen, Nehemiah Wade.; Size: 75 x 87mm. (front border design 71 x 83mm; back blank).
    The certificate is printed in red and black ink. In the lower right corner is a blue-black circular seal depicting a bird looking at a palm tree with a mill stone weight on top; the motto above reads: "Opressa surgit" (Having been oppressed it rises up). This is similar to the Continental currency $1 emblem, "Depressa resurgit." Five signatures in brown ink. In this, as in several but not all notes, it is apparent that the top signer also numbered the note. The blank back of this certificate has a faded annotation written in a brown ink. The "roa" in the upper right corner of the back is a modern annotation in pencil.
- Georgia Currency May 4, 1778GeorgiaMay 4, 1778, GA 05/04/78; W. Lancaster;
  A typeset emission of ฃ150,000 in bills of credit to be paid from proceeds acquired out of the seizure of Tory estates as established in the act of May 4, 1778. Printed in red and black by W. Lancaster of Savannah, with a greenish blue seal. There are five signers on each bill. Denominations printed were: $20, $30 and $40 notes.
  - Twenty Dollars329 329, 102; Signers: William Few, Thomas Netherclift, William Maxwill, William O'Bryen, Nehemiah Wade.; Size: 89 x 173mm. (front border design 81 x 152mm; back border design 78 x 109mm).
    Printed with red and black ink. In the lower right corner of the front is a greenish-blue circular seal depicting a coiled rattlesnake ready to strike. The motto above, which is also on the back of the bill printed in red, reads: "Nemo me impune lacesset" (No one will provoke me with impunity). There are four varieties of this note, two of which have a floral designs on the outer row of the left border, as in our example, and two of which have circular designs instead. The two varieties of floral designs are distinguished by the number of ornaments in the bottom border. Starting from the ornament in the lower right corner and counting towards the left, one will find either 17 or 20 ornaments before coming to a small vertical bar. Our example has 20 ornaments before the bar. There are some holes in our note over the ends of the second and third signatures.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EANA mail bid auction 01/13/96, lot 353.
  - Forty Dollars3513 3513, 103; Signers: Charles Kent, William Few, Richard Wylly, William O'Bryen, Nehemiah Wade.; Size: 84 x 154mm. (front border design 81 x 152mm; back border design 78 x 110mm).
    Printed with red and black ink. There is a Greenish blue seal on the front left margin with the GEORGIA printed in cursive script. In the lower right corner is a greenish-blue circular seal depicting a dove holding an olive branch in its beak while below is a hand holding a dagger. The motto on the back of the bill printed in red, reads: "Aut pax, aut bellum in utroque paratus" (Either war or peace, prepared for both). There are two varieties of this note; both have a floral designs on the outer row of the left border distinguished by the number of ornaments in the bottom border. Starting from the ornament in the lower right corner and counting towards the left, one will find either 17 or 20 ornaments before coming to a small vertical bar. Our example has 20 ornaments before the bar. There is a tear in our note near the upper right corner of the front.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr, Numismatic Endowment from the EAHA mail bid auction 02/12/2000, lot 361.
- Georgia Currency October 16, 1786GeorgiaOctober 16, 1786, GA 10/16/86; John E. Smith; Abernethie
  An emission of ฃ50,000 in bills of credit to be loaned on real estate mortgage security according to the act of August 14, 1786. The legal tender status of this issue was revoked as of August 14, 1790. As with all Revolutionary era Georgia currency it was valid for paying taxes at the rate of $1,000 in paper for $1 in specie until November 13, 1786 when all issues became unredeemable. Printed by John E. Smith of Augusta on paper from Holland bearing the watermark "Honig and zoonen". The vignette of the Georgia constitution, which includes the motto: "Pro bono publico" (For the good of the public), was engraved by Abernethie. Backs are blank. There are three signatures on the three higher denominations and two signatures on the three lower denominations. Denominations printed were: 6d, 1s, 2s6d, 5s, 10s and 20s.
  - Twenty Shillings8008 8008, 104; Signers: George Jones, W. Freeman, W. Steele.; Size: 79 x 157mm. (front border design 75 x 154mm; back blank).
    Numbering and one signature in a faded red ink ink with two other signatures in brown ink. Denominated as 20s and £1. On the left portion of the note is a large metal cut consisting of a left border design and a draped vignette containing a parchment labelled "The Constitution of the State of Georgia 1777." The scroll above bears the motto: "Pro bono publico" (For the good of the public). Below this, the cut also contains a frame for the serial number. In the lower border of the serial number frame is a black strip with white letters reading "Abernethie Sc[ulptute], for the engraver. The right two-thirds of the note is typeset, with typset design borders. This example has a purple stain running along the bottom border of the typeset portion of the note. That margin states: "(design) £1 (design) Augusta: Printed by John E. Smith. (design) £1 (two designs)" In the paper chain lines are evident but no watermark is visible on this specimen. The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 12/2/95 lot 437. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Louisiana Currency January 1, 1720LouisianaJanuary 1, 1720, LA 01/01/20; ;
  The first of three typeset emissions of the Banque Royale. The notes were hand numbered with written signatures (added by the deputies of the officers named on the notes) except for the 10 livres note which had printed signatures. The backs were blank. Denominations in this issue were: 10, 100, 1,000 and 10,000 livres Tournois notes.
  - 100 Livres Tournois1667581 1667581, 105; Signers: signatures of three deputies.; Size: 103 x 166 mm.
    The text translates as: [Top line] One Hundred Tournois pounds. [Main text] The Bank promises to pay the Bearer at sight One Hundred Tournois pounds in Silver Specie, value received At Paris the first of January one thousand seven hundred twenty. [Signatures] Viewed (i.e. inspected) for Mr. Fenellon (signed by a deputy); Signed for Mr. Bourgeois (signed by a deputy); Controlled for Mr. Durevest (signed by a deputy). Jean Baptiste de Fnelon was the Inspector for the Bank, tienne Bourgeois was the Treasurer and Durevest was the Comptroller. This note was impressed with the bank seal. The indent shows BAN from BANQUE ROYALE. The paper is watermarked with "Billet de Banque" (Banknote) in cursive script. This example shows the "e Banque Billet d" (read in the same direction as the indent). There are also four chain lines visible in the paper. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. endowment from EAHA auction of August 22, 1998, lot 368, graded as choice crisp about uncirculated.
- Louisiana Currency July 1, 1720LouisianaJuly 1, 1720, LA 07/01/20; ;
  The second of three typeset emissions of the Banque Royale (see the entry under the previous emission, dated of January 1, 1720, for a general introduction to the series). The 1,000 and 10,000 livres notes of the prior emission were to be taken out of circulation and the notes printed in this emission were to be given in exchange for them. As this was an exchange issue the word "Division" appears above the text. As with the previous issue the notes were hand numbered. The backs were blank. The 100 livres note had written signatures (added by the deputies of the officers named on the notes) while the 10 livres note had printed signatures. Denominations in this issue were: 10 and 100 livres Tournois notes.
  - 10 Livre Tournois401301 401301, 106; Signers: Printed signatures of Giraudeau, Delanauze and Granet.; Size: 89 x 151mm.
    The text is translated as: [Top line] Ten Tournois pounds. [Line two] Division. [Main text] The Bank promises to pay the Bearer at sight Ten Tournois pounds in Silver Specie, value received At Paris the first of July one thousand seven hundred twenty. [signatures] Viewed (i.e. inspected) for Mr. Fenellon (signed by a deputy); Signed for Mr. Bourgeois (signed by a deputy); Controlled for Mr. Durevest (signed by a deputy). Jean Baptiste de Fnelon was the Inspector for the Bank, tienne Bourgeois was the Treasurer and Durevest was the Comptroller. This note was impressed with the bank seal. The indent shows BAN from BANQUE ROYALE. The paper is watermarked with "Billet de Banque" (Banknote) in cursive script. This example shows the full "Billet de Banque" (read from the back of the note on the same end as the indent). There are also three chain lines visible in the paper. The back is blank.
    Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. endowment from EANA auction of Jan. 18, 1997, lot 280.
- Louisiana Currency September 2, 1720LouisianaSeptember 2, 1720, LA 09/02/20; ;
  The third and final typeset emission of the Banque Royale (see the entry under the first emission, dated January 1, 1720, for a general introduction to the series). The notes of prior emissions were to be taken out of circulation and exchanged for the notes in this emission. As this was another exchange issue the word "Division" with the date of the authorization appears above the text. As with the previous issues the notes were hand numbered but the signatures were only printed. The backs were blank. Denominations in this issue were: 10 and 50 livres Tournois notes.
  - 50 Livres Tournois362425 362425, 107; Signers: Printed signatures of Giraudeau, Delanauze and Granet.; Size: 110 x 160 mm.
    The text is translated as: [Top line] Fifty Tournois pounds. [Line two] Division Ordered by the act of 2 September 1720. [Main text] The Bank promises to pay the Bearer at sight Fifty Tournois pounds in Silver Specie, value received At Paris the tenth of September one thousand seven hundred twenty. [Signatures] Viewed (i.e. inspected) for Mr. Fenellon (signed in print by a deputy); Signed for Mr. Bourgeois (signed in print by a deputy); Controlled for Mr. Durevest (signed in print by a deputy). Jean Baptiste de Fnelon was the Inspector for the Bank, ƒtienne Bourgeois was the Treasurer and Durevest was the Comptroller. The note was impressed with the bank seal. The indent shows the tip of an E and the top of the letters ROY from BANQUE ROYALE; there is a notch tear at the O. The paper is watermarked with "Billo de Banque" (Banknote) in cursive script. The word Billo should be Billet. This example shows the "e Banque Billo de B" (read in the same direction as the indent). There are also five chain lines visible in the paper. The back is blank.
    Acquired from an anonymous donor.
- Maryland Currency 1733Maryland1773, MD 1733; ;
  This is the first Maryland issue. It consisted of ฃ90,000 in indented bills of credit which were to pass as lawful tender for most debts, except for fees due to a minister or an officer. In order to replace the then current use of tobacco as money, each taxpayer was to be given 30s in notes in return for burning 150 pounds of tobacco. The notes were to be redeemed by the loan office starting in 1748 with profits realized through investments made in Bank of England stock (the stock was purchased from the proceeds of a tax on tobacco exports). The entire emission was replaced in 1749 with one third paid off in sterling from investment profits and two thirds exchanged for new bills. The plates were engraved in England and the paper was watermarked "Maryland." Five bills of the same denomination were engraved on one sheet, the bills being distinguished by one to five stars placed after the denomination in the lower left corner. The notes were hand dated, with two signers. Denominations printed were: 1s, 1s6d, 2s6d, 5s, 10s, 15s and 20s.
  - Two Shillings, Six Pence, 108; Signers: [unsigned]; Size: 71 x 240mm (length from the inner border of the indent design to the edge of the note: 165mm, length of indent design 27.5mm).
    There were five notes of this denomination printed as a single sheet. Our example has two stars after the denomination in the lower left corner of the note (II.s. VI.d. **), hence it was the second bill from the top on the sheet. The stub is still attached and the note was never signed or numbered. The arms of the colony appear in the upper right. The note was torn in the center and repaired. The paper is watermarked, "Maryland." The back is blank.
    EANA mail bid auction 1/13/96 lot 356. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
- Maryland Currency March 1, 1770Annapolis, MarylandMarylandMarch 1, 1770, MD 03/01/70; Anne Catherine Green and William Green; Thomas Sparrow
  An emission of $318,000 in indented bills without legal tender status to be used for loans. They were to be payable from October 10, 1781, to April 10, 1782, at the rate of 4s6d sterling per dollar or equivalent in gold or silver. However by an act of October 17, 1780 all currency issues before 1776 were to be exchanged at a rate of forty old dollars for one new dollar until March 20, 1781, at which time they became void. This issue following the January 1, 1767, Maryland issue is the second issue to use the term dollar. Printed by Anne Catherine Green and William Green in Annapolis. Border cuts for this issue (and for the previous issue of January 1, 1767) were engraved by Thomas Sparrow, an Annapolis goldsmith and friend of the coiner John Chalmers. The nature prints on the back has previously been used for the January 1, 1767, emission printed by Jonas Green. Each bill had two signers and the $1/3 bill and higher denominations had what were termed "secret marks" to deter and detect counterfeits. Although such marks appeared on several colonial issues they were always exactly copied by counterfeiters. Denominations printed were: $1/9, $1/6, $2/9, $1/3, $1/2, $2/3, $1, $2, $4, $6 and $8.
  - One-Sixth Dollar9922 9922, 109; Signers: Robert Couden, John Clapham.; Size: 62 x 116mm. (front border trimmed, back border: 43 x 104)
    Signed and numbered in brown ink with the state arms on the front and a nature print of fern leaves on the back. As secret anti-counterfeiting marks commas were added to the Romna Numeral date. There are three engraved borders on the front with the bottom border typeset.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 447. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - One-Half Dollar12030 12030, 110; Signers: John Clapham, Robert Couden.; Size: 65 x 118mm. (front border 62 x trimmed; back border: 43 x 103)
    Signed and numbered in brown ink with the state arms on the front and a nature print of two leaves on the back. As a secret anti-counterfeiting mark a small letter "a" was added between "Half" and "Dollar" on the top line of text opposite the serial number. There are three engraved borders on the front with the bottom border typeset. In the center of ther top border are the initials T.S. for the engraver Thomas Sparrow. On the back the bottom line of text has been set upside down.
    EANA mail bid auction 04/20/96 lot 448. Purchased through the Robert H. Gore, Jr. Numismatic Endowment.
  - One Dollar11950 11950, 111; Signers: John Clapham, Robert Couden.; Size: 64 x 118mm.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. This note contains a picture of a Spanish milled dollar and the Maryland state arms. As a secret anti-counterfeiting mark the 'N' in "INDENTED" is rotated 180 degrees. The back of this bill originally had a nature print but has been completely backed with a brown paper. There are three engraved border cuts and a typeset lower border. In the upper margin is the signature of the engraver of the cuts, "T. Sparrow Sculpt."
    Donated by Felix Roppert of New York City in January 1936.
  - Two Dollars8562 8562, 112; Signers: John Clapham, Robert Couden.; Size: 63 x 111mm.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. This note contains pictures of two Spanish milled dollars and the Maryland state arms. As an secret anti-counterfeiting mark there is a period over the 'a' in "Rate." The back of this bill originally had a nature print but has been completely backed with a brown paper. There are three engraved border cuts and a typeset lower border.
  - Two Dollars12663 12663, 113; Signers: John Clapham, Robert Couden.; Size: 63 x 111mm.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. This note contains pictures of two Spanish milled dollars and the Maryland state arms. As an secret anti-counterfeiting mark there is a period over the 'a' in "Rate." There are three engraved border cuts and a typeset lower border. On the back is a nature print of leaves and branches. The bottom line of text on the back has been set upside down. This bill has split into two pieces.
  - Two Dollars17700 17700, 114; Signers: Robert Couden, John Clapham.; Size: 63 x 111mm.
  - Four Dollars8095 8095, 115; Signers: Robert Couden, John Clapham.; Size: 67 x 111mm.
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. On the front is the Maryland arms and three engraved border cuts with the bottom margin typeset. In the top margin is the signature of the engraver, "T. Sparrow Sculpt." As an secret anti-counterfeiting mark each 'N' in "LONDON" is rotated 180 degrees. On the back is a nature print consisting of branches and a leaf. The leaf has the initials "I.G" on it for Jonas Green. These nature prints has originally been designed for and used in the January 1, 1767 emission, which had been printed by Jonas Green. In this 1770 issue, the printer, William Green, used the prints unchanged. On the back the bottom line of text has been set upside down. This example is in two pieces.
  - Six Dollars2557 2557, 116; Signers: Robert Couden, John Clapham.; Size: 68 x 129mm
    Numbered and signed in brown ink. On the front is the Maryland arms and three engraved border cuts with the bottom margin typeset. As an secret anti-counterfeiting mark a dot follows "Assembly"; there are also three type sizes in "MARYLAND". Along the right border is "I.G. Printer" for Jonas Green, who printed the January 1, 1767 emission from which this 1770 emission was copied by the printer William Green. Also in the right border is, "T. Sparrow Sculp." for the engraver of the border cuts. These names are also mentioned in the top border with "I.G. Printer" to the left and "T.S. Sculpt" to the right; "I.G." is also found in the lower right margin in the scroll work. On the back is a nature print with two two types of leaves, on the leaf to the right are the initials "I.G." In our example the back bears a handwritten inscription: "£2 5[s] 6d" and to the right is what appears to be a '6' and a name, possibly "Tallner". This bill is split into two pieces.
  - Six Dollars7067 7067, 117; Signers: John Clapham, Robert Couden.; Size: 65 x 123mm.